Guide to the Papers of John G. Mason MC.88
New York University Archives
John G. Mason Papers
1963-1978
New York University Archives
MC.88
2.75 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 1 flat box
The John G. Mason Collection contain various records from many of the student and student faculty organizations active at NYU during the years 1962 to 1978. The primary focus of this collection is student and faculty opposition to the Vietnam War between the years 1965 and 1971. The records include organizational position papers, flyers, and posters. These materials are a representative sample of information on student activity and do not contain comprehensive documentation of all student groups.
Arrangement
Although the original order was noted and recorded, the collection has been reorganized so that the series are arranged chronologically by content (except where specially noted as exceptions), with the aim of facilitating research access. The collection consists of eight series, seven of which are boxed together; one of which is stored in the flat files.
The collection has been organized into eight series:
Historical Overviews, Personal Papers and Ephemera
SDS Material, Chi-Reston Papers, SDS "Successors"
New York University (NYU) Student Organization Activity
New University Conference (NUC) Materials
Library and Cafeteria Workers--National Students' Strike of 1970
NYU Administrative Documents
Student Movement Organizations
Student Organization Posters
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Other materials on the SDS, NYU student involvement, the Anti-War Movement, NYU's transformation of the 1960s and 1970s are contained within the University Archives, the Tamiment/Wagner Archives, and NYU's Bobst Library. A short list of the collateral sources would include:
Chancellor Heald's Administrative and Personal Papers Collection. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Chancellor Hester's Administrative and Personal Papers Collection. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Chancellor Sawhill's Administrative and Personal papers Collection. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Minutes of the New York University Trustee Council, 1962-1976. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Miller, Peter. "Violets on the Picket Line," Public History Records, NYU History Department, New York City, New York.
Myers, David R. Toward A History of the New Left: Essays From Within The Movement.
Photographic Records of Student Protests 1962-1978, New York University Archives Photographic Collection. University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Reports of the Chancellors of New York University, 1962-1976. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Reports of the Secretary of New York University, 1962-1976. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Reports of the Treasurer of New York University, 1962-1976. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Still, Bayrd. Administrative Papers and Personal Records. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Students For A Democratic Society (SDS) Records 1934-1966. Tamiment Library/Wagner Labor Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Students for A Democratic Society: Alternative Education Project, Radical America.
Unger, Irwin. The Movement: A History of the American New Left, 1955-1977.
University Christian Foundation Records, 1906-1980. New York University Archives, Bobst Library, New York University, New York.
Scope and Contents
The John G. Mason Papers are a personal collection of records that document NYU student activity and the student movement. The collection is the result of selective recordkeeping on the part of the collection's creator and donor. Mason was an active or ex-officio member of many of NYU's student organizations during the late 1960s. As a result, several students and faculty members entrusted him with their materials regarding this period. The collection covers the period 1962-1978, although the bulk of the materials are concentrated upon the period from 1965 through 1971. It is also important to note that while there are some materials from the University Heights campus in the collection, the bulk of the material is from the Washington Square campus.
The primary collection materials include: leaflets, organizational position papers, flyers, posters, handbills, public-relations pamphlets, university and student publications, newsletters, newspapers, analytical, financial, and strategic documents, and multiple analyses of the university's structure, officers, trustees, financial activity, professoriate, and curriculum. The collection also includes ephemera such as buttons and organizational membership cards. Included as well is 16mm film footage of a student and faculty protest against Dow Chemical Corporation recruiters on campus. This footage was filmed by NYU Campus Security. These materials exist as manuscript, typescript, mimeographic reproduction, printed matter and freehand drawings.
Biographical Note
A member of the interdepartmental Albert Schweitzer Program in the Humanities for undergraduates at New York University, John G. Mason was active in the Students for a Democratic Society and other university student organizations of the 1960s-1970s. Like many other students of the period, Mason was involved in organizations which were funded and/or organized by the university, and also in organizations which were external to the university and self-funded.
Mason was strongly affected by his matriculation in the Schweitzer Program, which was established by New York State in 1965 and given an endowed chair. The Schweitzer Program was led by Dr. Conor Cruise O'Brien from 1965-1969. Dr. O'Brien, a Left-opposition politician in the Republic of Ireland (Eire), and a longtime contributing editor to the Atlantic Monthly, had a significant intellectual influence upon Mason and other members of his student leadership cohort (see the general history of NYU contained within the collection).
In his collected correspondence Mason also attributed a portion of his political views to his experiences in Paris, France, which he visited in 1968 in the aftermath of the "Paris Commune" and the national students' strike, which strongly affected French educational policy through the mid-1970's.
After his involvement with NYU and the student movement as an undergraduate, Mason went on to get a M.A. from NYU's Politics Department and then a Ph.D. from CUNY.
Access Restrictions
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact New York University Archives, (212) 998-2641, university-archives@nyu.edu
Provenance
The John G. Mason papers are a personal collection of records of NYU student activity and the student movement. John G. Mason personally arranged the collection and titled the folders. The collection is the result of selective recordkeeping and possibly selective culling.
The collection was partially accessioned by the University Archives in early 1978. Additional material was accessioned throughout 1978.
Leaflets (printed works).; Fliers (printed matter); Correspondence.; Civil rights movements -- United States.; Radicals -- New York (State) -- New York.; Students -- Political activity; Newspapers.; Student movements |z France.; Student movements |z New York (State) |z New York.; Newsletters.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975. -- Protest movements; Student-administrator relationships.; Buttons (information artifacts).; Posters.; Financial records; Drawings (visual works); Film.; Clippings (information artifacts); Motion pictures (visual works).; Diaries; Publications (documents); Membership cards.; Black Panther Party; O'Brien, Conor Cruise, 1917-2008; New University Conference (U.S.); Mason, John, 1948; New York University; Nguyễn, Huệ Chi; Peace and Freedom Party (U.S.); Reston, James, 1946-; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.).
- Series I: Historical Overviews, Personal Papers and Ephemera, 1969-1977
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged chronologically but preceded by Mason's graphical map of NYU student organizations (1963-1978), and a general history of the 1960s and 1970s at NYU co-authored by Mason. Series I includes various membership cards, buttons, and ephemera.
  - General History and Information, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Buttons & Organization Membership Cards, [196-] - [197-] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled: notes poster collection location (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mason Correspondence & Diary, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: SDS Material, Chi-Reston Papers, SDS "Successors", 1962-1974
  Series II contains records regarding the creation of the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) at NYU, materials on the SDS's Radical Education Project at NYU, records from both the student and administration's viewpoints regarding the SDS-led demonstration against Ambassador Chi and James Reston's pro-Vietnam War presentations, and materials on what Mason termed "SDS successor" organizations.
  - SDS Period #1: Regional & NYU Chapter, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - SDS Period #1: Regional & NYU Chapter, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - SDS Period #2: Regional & NYU Chapter, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - SDS Period #2: Regional & NYU Chapter, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - SDS Radical Education Project:, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Account of Chi-Reston Demonstration, [1970] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NYU Administration Response to Chi-Reston Demonstration and Aftermath, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - SDS Successor Organizations, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series III: New York University (NYU) Student Organization Activity, 1965-1975
  Series III contains various student publications from the Washington Square campus during 1968-1975, some records from the New Student Union of 1965 and, in general, a group of records from the Weinstein Residence Hall, Washington Square Campus-All Square Congress, Faculty of Arts and Sciences-Graduate Students Organization, and the NYU Student President's Conference.
  - New Student Union-New York University, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Weinstein Residence & Library Materials, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - All Square Congress-New York University, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Graduate Student Organization Politics, 1967-1972* (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - NYU Student President's Conference: Proposal for a more Democratic University, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Vietnam Moratorium Duplicates: Graduate Student Organization, School of Education (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Homer Watt Lecture: The Writer & the Power Structure, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Various Student Publications, 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series IV: New University Conference (NUC) Materials, 1968-1975
  Series IV deals with the New University Conference (NUC), an Ann Arbor-based and socialist-influenced organization which was led primarily by faculty. Students active in the Anti-War Movement also played a significant role in the organization. NUC-NYU's activities fully reflected the national organization's concerns with providing leftist education alternatives for undergraduate and graduate students. Some of the NUC-NYU projects documented in this series are: the publication of NYU Inc., a financial and social analysis of NYU's Trustees Council, endowment investments, Law School, and financial ties to war contractors and the South African government; the early research for and support of the "University Without Walls" program at Washington Square, and involvement in the creation of the Metropolitan Studies Program; and finally, the Ivan Bennett Affair, to name only a few of the more prominent examples of NUC's activities.
  - NUC: National & Regional Materials I, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - NUC: National & Regional Materials I, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - NUC: National & Regional Materials II, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - NUC: N.Y.U Chapter (NUC-NYU), 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - NUC-NYU: Ivan Bennett Affair Papers, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - NUC-NYU: Raw Data for NYU Inc. I, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - NUC-NYU: Raw Data for N.U.U. Inc. II, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - NUC-NYU: Radical History Caucus, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - NUC-NYU: Study Group, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - NYU Center for Marxist Studies, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - NUC Newsletters, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - NYU President's Urban Studies Report and Early Metropolitan Studies Program, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - NYU Inc.: Posters Advertising Sale, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Political Science Association Reprint from APSA Newsletter vol. II, 1969, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - NUC & Strike Coordinating Committee Materials, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series V: Library and Cafeteria Workers--National Students' Strike of 1970, 1970-1971
  This series includes materials from the Library and Cafeteria Workers strike committees, records from the faculty-student strike coordinating committee for the academic side of the university, the participating departments, the coordinating committees of the buildings which students seized and occupied, and finally, a collection of student analyses of the strike which were written for Professor Fleming's class in the Politics Department. For an analysis of these events which is based primarily upon the records of the Cafeteria and Library workers' union local, and upon oral histories, see Peter Miller's video "Violets on the Picket Line." The video, as well as a research paper, are available for use at the Public History Program office in the NYU Department of History, 19 University Place, Fifth floor. Both the video and the paper are scheduled for accession by the University Archives.
  - Library & Cafeteria Workers Strike, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Worker--Student--University Issues, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - National Students Strike at NYU Diaries and Comments, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - National Students Strike: Flyers, Demands, News and Newspaper, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - National Students Strike: Courant, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - National Students Strike: N.Y.U Movement for a New Congress, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - National Students Strike: NYU Politics Department, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - National Students Strike: NYU Psychology Department, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - National Students Strike: NYU Strike Coordinating Committee, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - National Students Strike: Kimball, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Collective & Transcendental Students, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - National Students Strike: Various Other NYU Groups and Departments, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National Students Strike: Various Strike Related Documents, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - National Students Strike: General Press Releases and Publications, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - National Students Strike: Strike Issues of NYU Newspapers, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - National Students Strike: External Publications, Strike Issues, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - National Students Strike: Professor Fleming's Guide and Student Analyses, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Series VI: NYU Administrative Documents, 1964-1975
  This series contains three different classes of records which have been arranged chronologically by class: 1) those reports and press releases which indicated NYU's efforts to deal with specific problems in its student body that had been created by demographics, politics, economic circumstances, etc. (folder 49); 2) materials which presented NYU's long-range plans to the wider university community and the general public, and those internal reports and bulletins that fulfill the same purpose on a day to day level (folders 50-51); and finally, 3) a surveillance film from Campus Security which depicted a student-faculty demonstration in 1968, whose focus was the appearance of and pro-war speeches on campus by Ambassador Chi and James Reston (folder 52).
  - The University Viewpoint, 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - NYU Capital Program, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - University Reports & Bulletins, 1969-1975 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - NYU Surveillance Film of 3/6/68 Dow Chemical Demonstration, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series VII: Student Movement Organizations, 1967-1971
  Arranged chronologically by organization. These student groups arose out of the opposition to the Vietnam War, and included within their membership both students and non-university members.
  - Peace and Freedom Party Materials, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Campus Voice--Committee to End the War in Vietnam Materials, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - International Socialists: Regional Materials, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Black Student Activities: NYU, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Black Panther Defense Materials, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Gay Liberation Material, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Series VIII: Student Organization Posters, 1971
  This series contains one Anti War Conference Poster dated 1971. Other posters (dated 1962-1978) in this collection have been separated to the University Archives' Poster Collection.
  - Anti War Conference Poster, 1971 (Box Shared University Archives 004)